TAWFIK MOHAMMED OSMAN

tmosman@asu.edu • https://www.linkedin.com/in/tawfik-osman-11935b14a • +1 (480) 452-6734

SUMMARY

Ph.D. candidate in electrical engineering with two years of research experience in wireless communications and signal processing. Tawfik is seeking a full-time internship in simulation, integration and testing of wireless communication system and machine learning research.

EDUCATION

Electrical Engineering, PhD

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Communication Systems and Signal Processing – Advisor: Prof. Ahmed Alkhateeb.

May 2024

Research: Machine Learning Aided mmWave MIMO Beam Prediction and Localization.

First Semester | **GPA 4.0**

Master of Science in Engineering, Electrical Engineering Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering | Graduation: May 2021 | GPA: 3.68.

- Awards: MasterCard Scholars Foundation Scholarship | Fulton Undergraduate Research Initiative(FURI) Funding | Master's
 Opportunity for Research in Engineering (MORE) Funding.
- **Relevant Coursework**: Communication Systems, Digital Signal Processing, Detection and Estimation Theory, Digital Circuit Design, Wireless Networks, Communication Networks, Digital Communication, Python for Rapid Eng. Solutions.

Bachelor of Science, Electrical & Electronic Engineering

Ashesi University

Accra, Ghana

Graduation: May 2019 | *GPA*: 3.73.

• **Honors:** First Class Honors |

• Awards: MasterCard Foundation Scholar.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: Python | MATLAB | C&C++ | HTML \$ CSS.

Design: Cadence | Simulink | GNU Radio Companion | Linux Scripting

Hardware: NI USRP | Raspberry Pi | Jetson Nano & Xavier | Hardware Prototyping & Testing

Statistics: R-Studio | Tableau Software | Microsoft Excel.

Frameworks & Libraries: PyTorch | TensorFlow | NumPy | OpenCV | SciPy | Scikit-Learn | Matplotlib | Pandas | pyQt5 & tkinter | Sockets.

Certification: Deep Learning Specialization in Coursera by Andrew Ng.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Graduate Research Assistant

 $January\ 2021-present$

- Project: Functional Mapping of sub-GHz channel state information to the mmWave beam vectors, using datasets from a real dual-band Testbed

 Implemented a co-located dual-band Testbed consisting of a mmWave transceiver (Linear Phased Array RF module) and SIMO sub-
 - 6GHz transceivers (NI USRPs and microcontrollers).
 - Implemented end-to-end mmWave and sub-GHz communication using OFDM-based pilot sequences.
 - Developed the digital signal processing blocks in python to capture signals and estimate channel state information and beam vectors.
 - Collected, preprocessed, and built datasets of sub-6GHz channels and mmWave received power vectors
 - Developed a deep learning model that creates a functional mapping between the channel state information from sub-6GHz signals and mmWave beamforming vectors.

Project: Evaluating the Prototype of Reconfigurable Intelligent Surface (RIS) using a sub-6GHz transceiver Testbed in the field.

- Accomplished the control of RIS proof-of-concept prototype with microcontrollers and interfaced it with the sub-6GHz communication setup.
- Lead a month-long field test measurement, to verify the performance of the RIS system.
- Analyzed the received signal power from the RIS, to estimate the pathloss, power gain and coverage in Non-Line of Sight (NLOS) sub-6GHz transmission scenario.
- Integrated a camera system to the testbed, to facilitate RIS-aided sub-GHz channel estimation and terminal user localization.

Project: Employed Deep Learning and GPS positioning for Vision-Aided mmWave Beam Prediction.

- Interfaced GPS-RTK Board and Stereo camera to a mmWave Testbed using Python Programming, Socket library and ZED2's SDK.
- Collected, preprocessed, and analyzed the vision data (RGB), position data (Lat/Long) and the mmWave beam power vectors from a Vehicle-to-Infrastructure (V2I) mmWave communication setup.
- Leveraged on pre-trained Res-Net model and Multi-layered neural networks to develop a multi-modal mmWave beam predictor, capable of predicting the optimal beam direction from the preprocessed Vision data, and the GPS position data.

Tempe, AZ June 2020 - Aug. 2020

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Project: Machine Learning Aided Optimal Beam Prediction

- Contributed to building the signal processing blocks of a mmWave communication system's prototype.
- Integrated a Marvelmind Indoor Positioning System with the mmWave Testbed.
- Employed Pandas module to pre-process the raw datasets collected Integrated wireless system.
- Developed and tested a novel feed-forward neural network(mmWave Beam Predictor), using python modules from PyTorch framework.

Course Project: Developed a Multi-Layer Perceptron Classifier (MLPC) Model for classification problem.

- Built a binary classifier to detect whether there is a mine or rock in the surrounding of a Submarine.
- Employed Principal Component Analysis(PCA) to reduce the Dependent variables to an orthogonal dataset to prevent overfitting.
- The orthogonal dataset was standardized, splitted, trained and tested using modules from Scikit-Learn library.

WORK EXPERIENCES

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Graduate Service Assistant

May 2020 - December 2020

- Facilitated lab activities in coursework of Digital Design Fundamentals, using Intel DE10-Lite FPGA board to implement logic circuits.
- Supported the ASU Sync modality by assisting a faculty member in organizing and controlling the teaching and learning equipment.
- Successfully Held up to 2 hrs./week sessions to help students with their assignments and projects in Python and Machine learning.

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

January 2020 - May 2020

- Coordinated and assisted a faculty member in teaching a Python for Rapid Engineering Solution (EEE591) in a class of 140 students. And 40% of the class had grade A.
- Exploited the Scikit-learn library and utilized its classification algorithms such as Support Vector Machine, KNN, Logistic regression and Perceptron to build an optimized model capable of predicting 98% of counterfeit bills.
- Assisted students to build a CAD Tool Driver Program that utilizes the libraries of Python to generate an inverter-chain Hspice file with an optimized number of inverters and path effort, at a minimum path delay.

PUBLICATIONS AND ACTIVE RESEARCH PROJECTS

- T. Osman and A. Alkhateeb, "Leveraging on Deep Learning to Predict Optimal mmWave Beam Directions Using Sub-6GHz Channels Information from a MIMO Testbed." [Active project]
- G. Chara, T. Osman, A. Hredzak, N. Thawdar and A. Alkhaateeb, "Vision-Position Multi-Modal Beam Prediction using Real Millimeter Wave Datasets". Accepted to be presented at IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC). Austin TX, United States. 2022.
- G. C. Trichopoulos, P. Theofanopoulos, K. Bharath, S. Aditya, M. Anuj, O. Tawfik, S. Kumar, A. Sengar, A. Chang, and A. Alkhateeb. "Design Evaluation of Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces in Real-World Environment," submitted to IEEE Open Journal of the Communications Society, 2021. [Online]. Available: https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.07763.pdf
- G. Charan, T. Osman, and A. Alkhateeb, "Position Error Characterization and Denoising Using Computer Vision and 6G Communication Beams." Expected to be submitted to IEEE WCNC 2022. [internal review]